David Bauer

1411 Poxson Ave. Lansing, MI 48910 (901) 826-2984 | dbauer2718@gmail.com

QUALIFICATIONS SUMMARY

I am a biophysicist with 7 years of research experience in academia and industry, where I have focused on building hardware and software tools to answer scientific questions. I have experience in machine learning, data and image analysis, and software development.

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN FRANCISCO	
Ph.D. Biophysics	2015 - 2020
UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY	
B.A. Physics	2007 - 2011

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

University of California, San Francisco – Biophysics Department Postdoctoral Scholar Graduate Student 2020 2015 - 2020

- Analyzed 3D image data to measure flagellar lengths, resulting in the detection of novel statistically significant noise; Results submitted to *Current Biology*
- Designed and fabricated a microfluidic device for high throughput imaging of *Chlamydomonas* flagella to study organelle size control; Enabled critical flagellar regeneration experiments
- Collaborated with lab members to design and fabricate a microfluidic device for long term imaging of *Stentor* to study cell size control; Enabled critical size control monitoring experiments
- Used Amazon's Mechanical Turk to train machine learning algorithms to pick particles from Cryo-EM images; wrote software to optimize output from users on Mechanical Turk; results published in *Nature Methods*

Calico Life Sciences

 Consultant
 2019 - 2020

 Intern
 Fall 2018

- Integrated microscopy hardware components and microfluidics in Python for custom microscopy setup
- Wrote software to identify targets using computer vision
- Built a single-shot autofocus using deep learning, resulting in faster and more reliable imaging

University of California, San Francisco – Pharmacology Department Assistant Specialist

2013 - 2015

- Designed and built an illumination system to deliver optogenetic pulses of light with precise temporal and spatial resolution; results are published in *Cell Systems*
- Designed and built a compact phase contrast microscope capable of studying neuronal stem cell differentiation with live image analysis and feedback
- Built a computer and wrote software in MATLAB to control data acquisition, stage position, and illumination

Lawrence National Laboratory – Astrophysics Department

Research AssociateAnalyzed solar eclipse data to determine accurate stellar positions

- Designed curve-fitting algorithms to process star locations
- Performed error analysis for lens asymmetry, change in focal length, chromatic aberration, etc

University of California, Berkeley – Physics Department

Lab Assistant Summer 2011

- Reverse engineered and debugged a curve tracer program and educational signal processing and noise generating program (LabView)
- Analyzed specs, performed cost-benefit analysis, and upgraded documentation in order to implement a new Cd-Te X-Ray detector
- Tested various lab equipment, ranging from waveform generators to high voltage power supplies to avalanche photo diodes, for lab experiments

University of California, Berkeley – Police Department *Software Developer*

2012 - 2013

2011 - 2013

- Developed a program in C that reduced the workload of dispatchers and influenced day-to-day operation
- Responsible for developing a new database using Visual Basic for Applications and SQL
- Analyzed data and prepared reports for non-technical supervisor

SKILLS

• Languages/OS: Python, C, C++, Matlab, LabView, IDL, Microsoft Visual Basic, Linux/Unix, CAD

PUBLICATIONS

- **David Bauer**, Hiroaki Ishikawa, Kim Wemmer, Wallace Marshall. "Biological Noise in an Organelle Size Control System", submitted for review. Current Biology 2020 bioRxiv preprint: https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.31.276428v1
- **David Bauer**, Tatyana Mashukok, Wallace Marshall. "Building New Tools to Measure Noise in Organelle Size Control" Doctoral Dissertation, University of California San Francisco. ProQuest Dissertations Publishing. June 2020.
- Alex J. Hughes, Joseph D. Mornin, Sujoy K. Biswas, Lauren E. Beck, **David P. Bauer**, Arjun Raj, Simone Bianco, and Zev J. Gartner, *Nature Methods. "Quanti.us: a tool for rapid, flexible, crowd-based annotation of images"* VOL 15. August 2018. 587–590
- Cameron Sokholic, Yanxia Lui, **David Bauer**, Jade McPherson, Michael Broeker, Graham Heimberg, Lei S. Qi, David A. Sivak, and Matt Thomson, *Cell Systems*. "Transcription Factor Competition Allows Embryonic Stem Cells to Distinguish Authentic Signals from Noise" Vol 1, 117–129, August 26, 2015